The Samuel Gardner Papers
Yale University Music Library
The Samuel Gardner Papers
1913-1976
MSS 37
Yale University Music Library
4
(6 boxes)
Music, correspondence, photographs, and additional materials by and about the violinist, composer, and conductor Samuel Gardner (1891-1984).
Gardner, Samuel, 1891-1984
Conditions Governing Access
The Papers are open to researchers by appointment. There are no restricted materials in the collection. Please contact the Special Collections staff to schedule an appointment.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Samuel Gardner Papers were established in the Music Library of Yale University by Samuel Gardner in 1983.
Arrangement
In 5 series as follows: I. Music. II. Correspondence. III. Programs and Clippings. IV. Biographical Materials. V. Photographs.
Scope and Contents
The Samuel Gardner Papers document Gardner's varied career as a composer, violinist, conductor, and educator. The Papers hold sketches, manuscript scores, and printed editions of Gardner's musical compositions and pedagogical works. The Papers also include: correspondence to and from Gardner; programs, newspaper clippings, and reviews; photographs; and the transcript of an interview with Gardner made as part of Columbia University's Thomas A. Edison project.
Biographical / Historical
Samuel Gardner was born August 25, 1891, in Elizavethgrad, Russia, and was brought to the United States at the age of one. His family settled in Providence, Rhode Island, where Gardner attended elementary and high school. From the age of six, he studied violin with Felix Wendelschaefer. He continued his studies in Boston with Charles Martin Loeffler and Felix Winternitz from 1902 to 1908. At the New York Institute of Musical Art (1908-1913), Gardner studied violin with Fritz Kneisel and composition with Percy Goetschius.
Gardner made his New York debut in 1913, played 2nd violin in the Kneisel Quartet from 1914 to 1915, performed with the Chicago Symphony (several times as soloist) in 1915, and toured with the Elshuco Trio in 1916 and 1917. In addition to solo recitals, Gardner appeared as soloist with the New York Philharmonic under Stransky and Mengelberg, with the Philadelphia Orchestra under Stokowski, with the St. Louis, Chicago, and Los Angeles Symphonies, and in Germany and Holland. He premiered his own Violin Concerto in 1918 with the Boston Symphony under Monteux.
As a violin teacher, Gardner held appointments at the Institute of Musical Art (now the Juilliard School) from 1924 to 1941. He also taught at Columbia University, the University of Wisconsin, the Hartt School of Music, and the Atlanta School of music. Gardner published a number of pedagogical works which include a method for violin and his Harmonic Thinking school of string playing.
Gardner's conducting appearances included the premiere of his symphonic poem New Russia in 1921 with the Philadelphia Orchestra and the first performance of his Broadway (1924) with the Boston Symphony in 1930. From 1938 to 1939, Gardner conducted for the Federal Music Project in New York, and in 1946 he became the first Conductor and Music Director of the Staten Island Symphony.
Gardner received a prize from the Pulitzer Foundation for his Second String Quartet (1918) and an honorary doctorate from the New York College of Music (1939). The composer of many violin works, Gardner was especially renowned for From the Canebrake, which is still a standard encore piece for violinists. He died in New York on January 23, 1984.
Composers -- Correspondence; Concertos (Violin) -- Scores and parts; Music -- United States -- 20th Century; Violin and piano music -- Scores and parts; Violinists -- Correspondence; Betti, Adolfo; Damrosch, Walter, 1862-1950; Dykema, Peter W. (Peter William), 1873-1951; Erskine, John, 1879-1951; Flesch, Carl, 1873-1944; Gardner, Samuel, 1891-1984; Hartmann, Arthur, 1881-1956; Heifetz, Jascha, 1901-1987; Mannes, David, 1866-1959; Mason, Daniel Gregory, 1873-1953; Ozawa, Seiji, 1935-; Sanders, Robert L., 1906-1974; Smith, David Stanley, 1877-1949; Spalding, Albert, 1888-1953; Stringham, Edwin John, 1890-1974; Williams, John, 1932-; Yost, Gaylord, 1888-1958
- Music, Series I
  - Concert Music by Gardner, I.A
    - Abstract tone moods for orchestra.
      General
      see Splashes of color, arr.
    - Bird, say whither thy flight.
      see [Songs (1916)]
    - [Broadway (1924)] Broadway (1924); an orchestral fantasy / by Samuel Gardner., 1 manuscript score (74 p.); 43 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Holograph in ink.
      For full orchestra, organ, 3 saxophones and banjo.
      Corrections in pencil, ink, and pasted in.
      On title page: New York, 1924. First performance by Boston Symphony Orchestra in Boston, April 19, 1930. Conducted by the composer.
      At end: OK. Final check. 1978.
      2 copies. 2nd copy bound photocopy.
    - [Broadway (1924)] (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Negative microfilm of manuscript score.
    - [Broadway (1924)] Broadway (1924) / Samuel Gardner., 71 manuscript parts; 34 cm. (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
      Copyist's manuscript in ink.
      Corrections by the composer in pencil and pasted in.
      Parts for: picc/flI-III/obI-II/Eh/E-flat cl/clI-II/bc/bsnI-II/cbsn/hnI-IV/alto saxI-III/tptI-III/tbnI-III/tuba/org/harpI-II/timp/perc/tenor banjo/vlnI/vlnII/vla/vc/cb.
    - [Broadway (1924), Sketches] Excerpts from Broadway., 18 manuscript p. of music; various sizes. (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Holograph in pencil and ink.
      Corrections and additions for orchestra of Broadway (1924).
    - [Concerto, violin, orchestra, op. 18, E minor] Concerto in e minor for violin and orchestra, op. 18 / Samuel Gardner. -- Revised version., 1 manuscript score (109 p.); 34 cm. (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Corrections in pencil and pasted in.
      Dates of revisions and performances written on title page in pencil and ink.
      Dates of sketches and performances written at end in ink.
      Newspaper clippings and reviews of first performance in Providence, RI, pasted on inside cover and title page
    - [Concerto, violin, orchestra, op. 18, E minor] Concerto in e minor for violin and orchestra, op. 18 / by Samuel Gardner., 58 manuscript parts; 36 cm. (Box 3, Folder 1-7)
      Parts for: picc/flI-III/obI-II/clI-II/bsnI-II/hnI-II /tptI-III/tbnI-III/tuba/timp/harp/bells /xylo/vlnI/vlnII/vla/vc/cb.
    - The death bed. (Box 3, Folder 1-7)
    - [Coquetterie] Coquetterie, op. 26 / Samuel Gardner. -- New York: G. Schirmer, c1940., 1 score (7 p.) + 1 part (3 p.); 31 cm. (Box 4, Folder 1)
      For violin and piano.
      Corrections, fingerings, and rehearsal markings added in ink by the composer.
      Pl. no.: 37987
    - [From the canebrake] From the canebrake, op. 5, no. 1 / Samuel Gardner. -- New York: G. Schirmer, c1918., 1 score (6 p.) + 1 part ([1 p.]); 31 cm. (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Corrections in pencil and ink.
      3 copies.
      On p. 1 of 1 copy: This copy has last dynamics, Sept. 1976.
      1 copy is photocopy of piano part only, showing composer's corrections and metronome markings.
      Pl. no.: 28000
    - [From the canebrake, arr.] From the canebrake for orchestra, op. 5, no. 1 / by Samuel Gardner., 1 manuscript score (9 p.); 34 cm. (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Holograph, signed, in pencil.
      On title page: Done in May 1919, noted in Sept. 1974, 55 years ago. My orch. was better than Schmid's.
      At end: May 1919.
    - [From the canebrake, arr.] From the canebrake / Samuel Gardner., 1 manuscript score (12 l.); 36 cm. (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Photocopy of holograph.
      For orchestra.
      At end: Sept 28, 1976.
    - [From the canebrake, arr.] From the canebrake, op. 5, no. 1 / Samuel Gardner. -- New York: G. Schirmer, c1922., 22 parts; 31 cm. (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Parts for:
      pno-conductor/flI-II/obI-II/clI-II/bsnI-II/hnI-IV /tptI-II/tbnI-III/harp/bells/xyl/vln obligato/vlnI/vlnII/vla/vc/cb.
      All but piano conductor and violin obligato are photocopies.
      Pub. no.: Galaxy, No. 205
      Pl. no.: 30653
    - [From the canebrake] From the canebrake / Samuel Gardner., 3 manuscript parts; 28 cm. (Box 4, Folder 3)
      To be added to orchestral arr.(?)
      Parts for: picc/timp/drums.
      2 copies of part for drums.
      Includes 1 p. of composer's revisions in pencil, dated Aug. & Sept. 1974.
    - [From the canebrake, arr.] From the canebrake / S. Gardner; arranged by H. Gardner., 78 parts; 32 cm. (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
      Photocopy of arranger's manuscript
      Arr. for band.
      Parts for: picc/fl I-II/obI-II/Eh/clI-IV/alto cl/bass cl/bsn/alto saxI-II/tenor saxIII-IV/bari sax/cornetI-III/tpt/hnI-IV/baritoneI-II/tbnI-III/bass tbn/tuba/cb/timp/drums/xyl/harp.
      Includes list of parts available, composer's holograph in pencil, 2 p.
    - [From the canebrake, arr.] Canebrake for concert string quartet, 1 manuscript score (3 p.); 35 cm. (Box 4, Folder 6)
      Holograph in pencil.
      Arr. for string quartet.
      On caption: First draft - June 1966. Revisions added here - Feb 1967.
      "For Leonard Davis & Philharmonic Quartet."
    - [From the canebrake, arr.] From the canebrake for string quartet / Samuel Gardner., 1 manuscript score (3 p.); 35 cm. (Box 4, Folder 6)
      On caption: 2nd draft - Feb. 1967. Final revisions - May 1967 after hearing twice by string quartet.
      "For Leonard David - viola."
    - [From the canebrake, arr.] From the canebrake for string quartet / by Samuel Gardner., 1 manuscript score (4 p.) + 4 manuscript parts; 33 cm. (Box 4, Folder 6)
      Corrections pasted in.
      On vln I part: New arrangement June 1966, originally composed in 1915.
      2 copies, 2nd copy is photocopy.
    - [From the canebrake, arr.] Canebrake for violin in 4 parts., 1 manuscript score (2 l.); 35 cm. (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Arr. for violin ensemble.
      On caption: Srpt. 29, 1968 - in one day.
    - [From the canebrake, arr.] From the canebrake for violin ensemble in 4 parts / Samuel Gardner., i manuscript score (4 l.); 32 cm. (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Corrections in pencil.
      On caption: Sept. 1968, New York.
      "This arrangement specially prepared for the Elizabeth Chapman violin ensemble."
    - [From the canebrake, arr.] From the canebrake for string trio; violin, viola, cello., 1 manuscript score (2 l.); 35 cm. (Box 4, Folder 8)
      Arr. for violin, viola, and cello.
      On caption: Start Sept. 7, 1975.
      "Specially arranged for my dear friend and pupil Barbara Gambrill Murray and her trio."
    - [From the canebrake, arr.] From the canebrake for string trio, op. 5, no. 1 / Samuel Gardner., 1 manuscript score (2 p.); 35 cm. (Box 4, Folder 8)
      Rehearsal nos. in ink.
      On cover: Fall 1925. Specially arranged for Barbara Murray.
    - [From the canebrake, arr.] From the canebrake for string trio / Samuel Gardner., 3 manuscript parts; 30 cm. (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - [From the canebrake, arr.] From the canebrake, op. 5, no. 1 / Samuel Gardner. -- New York: G. Schirmer, c1918., 1 score (5 p.) + 1 part ([1 p.]); 31 cm. (Box 4, Folder 9)
      Arr. for viola and piano.
      On cover: Corrected for dynamics. SG
      Pl. no.: 44152
    - Four songs. (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - [Hebraic fantasy] Hebraic fantasy for two violins and piano / by Samuel Gardner., 1 manuscript score (15 l.); 32 cm. (Box 4, Folder 10)
      On cover: All corrected with original and xerox copies. All unnecessary accents from no. 12 now out. Feb. 12, 1979.
      "To Joseph Fuchs, etc."
    - [Impromptus, violin, piano, G minor] Two impromptus for violin and piano / by Samuel Gardner., 1 manuscript score (7 p.) + 1 manuscript part ([2 p.]); 34 cm. (Box 4, Folder 11)
      Originally titled Rhapsodie for violin and piano.
      Sketches in pencil at end and on back of violin part.
      Incomplete: Lacks 1 impromptu.
    - [Impromptus, violin, piano, op. 21, B minor] Impromptu for violin and piano, op. 21 / Samuel Gardner., 1 ms score (9 p.) + 1 manuscript part (4 p.); 34 cm. (Box 4, Folder 12)
      On cover: Rearrange as 2 compositions in one book.
      Dated 6/29/37.
    - [Jazzetto] Jazzetto for violin and piano / by Samuel Gardner. -- New York: Carl Fischer, 1925., 1 score (11 p.); 29 cm. (Box 4, Folder 13)
      Publisher's master sheets (printed in reverse)
      Corrections in ink.
      Pl. no.: 23291-13
    - [Night in the Rockies] Night in the Rockies, op. 8 / Samuel Gardner. -- New York: Carl Fischer, c1923., 1 score (5 p.) + 1 part ([1 p.]); 31 cm. (Box 4, Folder 14)
      Pub. no.: Sheet music edition B. 1245
      Pl. no.: 22851-4
    - [Preludes, violin, piano, op. 14] Five preludes for violin and piano, op. 14 / Samuel Gardner. -- New York: Carl Fischer, c1919., 1 score (5 v.) + 1 part (5 v.); 31 cm. (Box 4, Folder 15)
      Library's copy bound together.
      Contents: Prelude in b major -- Prelude quasi improvvisata -- Prelude in b minor -- Prelude in c major -- Prelude in g minor.
      Pl. no.: 21530-3, 21531-5, 21532-6, 21533-10, 21534-3
    - [Preludes, violin, piano, op. 15, no. 4, D major] Prelude no. 9, op. 15, no. 4 / Samuel Gardner. -- New York: G. Schirmer, c1924., 1 score (7 p.) + 1 part (2 p.); 31 cm. (Box 4, Folder 15)
      On cover: Revised copy 1955.
      Pl. no.: 31895c
    - [Quintets, piano, strings, op. 16, F minor] Quintet, in f minor for piano, two violins, viola and violoncello, op. 16 / by Samuel Gardner. -- [Boston]: Oliver Ditson, c1926., 1 score (50 p.) + 4 parts; 32 cm. (Box 4, Folder 16)
      Corrections in composer's hand.
      Photocopy.
      At head of title: To a soldier.
      Contents: Prologue "la vie" -- Capriccio -- Dans la foret "la mort" -- Epilogue.
      "To the memory of David Hochstein, killed in action, France, 1918."
      Pl. no.: 75665-50+48
    - The secret. (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - [Songs (1916). Bird, say whither thy flight] Bird, say whither thy flight = Voglein, wohin so schnell / Samuel Gardner; from the German by E. Geibel. -- New York: M. Witmark, c1916., 1 score (5 p.); 31 cm. (Box 4, Folder 17)
      For voice and piano.
      English and German words.
      On cover: Dedicated to Mrs. Morris Rosenwald. Any relation to Hans Rosenwald?
      Pl. no.: 15178-4
    - [Songs (1916). Death bed] The death bed / Samuel Gardner; lyric by Thomas Hood. -- New York: M. Witmark, c1916., 1 score (6 p.); 30 cm. (Box 4, Folder 17)
      English words.
      Pl. no.: 15179-5
    - [Songs (1916). Secret] The secret / Samuel Gardner; lyric by Arthur Penn. -- New York: M. Witmark, c1916., 1 score (3 p.); 31 cm. (Box 4, Folder 17)
      Text printed as poem on p. 1.
      Alternate title: O tender babe.
      Pl. no.: 15193-3
    - [Splashes of color] Splashes of color; abstract from tone moods for orchestra / by Samuel Gardner., 1 manuscript score (13 p.); 34 cm. (Box 4, Folder 18)
      For piano solo, with voice obligato in mvt. 3.
      Corrections and revisions in pencil.
      On cover: Five sketches for the piano. (Crossed out) If I can rewrite interesting enough I will leave a piano solo. 1918.
    - [Splashes of color, arr.] Splashes of color., 1 manuscript score (7 p.); 35 cm. (Box 4, Folder 18)
      Arr. for orchestra.
      On cover: Take to Fla. with extra 18 or 20 line paper.
      Incomplete: Lacks all after m. 20.
    - [Troubador] Troubador, op. 17, no.1 / Samuel Gardner. -- New York: G. Schirmer, c1944., 1 score (7 p.) + 1 part (3 p.); 31 cm. (Box 4, Folder 19)
      Two copies.
      Pl. no.: 40555
    - [Troubador, arr.] Troubador for violin solo with orchestral accompaniment, op. 17, no. 1 / by Samuel Gardner., 1 manuscript score (21 p.); 35 cm. (Box 4, Folder 20)
      Arr. for violin solo and orchestra.
      At end: October 1944, New York.
    - [Troubador, arr.] Troubador for violin solo and orchestra, op. 17, no. 1 / Samuel Gardner., 17 + 32 manuscript parts; 35 cm. (Box 4, Folder 21)
      Parts for: picc/fl/ob/cl/bsn/hn/tpt/tbn/timp/perc/harp/vln solo/vlnI/vlnII/vla/vc/cb.
      2 copies. 1st copy copyist's transparencies. 2nd copy photocopies.
    - [Two birds] Two birds / Samuel Gardner. -- New York: G. Schirmer, c1949., 1 score (5 p.) + 1 part (3 p.); 31 cm. (Box 4, Folder 22)
      Pl. no.: 41866
    - [Vaqueros] Vaqueros = Spanish cowboys, op. 19 / Samuel Gardner. -- Boston: Oliver Ditson, c1928., 1 score (7 p.) + 1 part (3 p.); 31 cm. (Box 4, Folder 23)
      Violin part is photocopy of "revised edition" with additions and corrections by the composer.
      Pl. no.: 76074 8
  - Pedagogical Works by Gardner, I.B
    (Designated as such by Gardner)
    - Babushka.
      see [Short pieces]
    - [Country moods] Country moods / by Samuel Gardner. -- New York: G. Schirmer, c1946., 1 score (25 p.) + 18 parts; 31 cm. (Box 5, Folder 1)
      For string orchestra with piano ad libitum.
      Cover signed: Samuel Gardner, June 1946.
      Contents: The cabin in the woods -- The little brook -- In the village.
      Pl. no.: 41278
    - [Elaborations Suzukiana] Elaborations Suzukiana: woven around the basic variations of the folk song "Twinkle, twinkle little star," arranged for violin by the distinguished teacher of Japan, Shinichi Suzuki / by Samuel Gardner. -- Boston: Boston Music, c1971., 1 score (8 p.) + 35 parts: 31 cm. (Box 5, Folder 2)
      For string orchestra and piano ad lib.
      Composer' s revisions in pencil.
      On cover: Score checked Dec-18-70
      Pl. no.: 13734-8
    - [Journey through the forest] Journey through the forest, first position; picturesque little violin pieces with a colorful piano accompaniment for the very first steps in solo and ensemble playing / by Samuel Gardner. -- Boston: Boston Music, c1949., 1 score (19 p.) + 1 part (18 p.): ills.; 31 cm. (Box 5, Folder 3)
      For violin in first position and piano.
      On cover: And pictures for coloring; Samuel Gardner
      Pl. no.: B.M.Co.10900
    - Little waltz in D. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Melancholy flute. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - [Miniatures, violin, piano] Five miniatures; simple first position pieces for violin, with piano accompaniment / by Samuel Gardner. -- Boston, Mass.: Boston Music, c1954., 1 score (11 p.) + 1 part (7 p.); 31 cm. (Box 5, Folder 4)
      Contains composer's markings.
      On cover: S.G.
      Contents: A little ballad -- Rollicking-frolicking -- Castanets --Goblins on tiptoe -- In old Russia.
      Pl. no.: B.M.Co.10945
    - [Music for string ensemble] Music for string ensemble, easy first position, first series; six familiar melodies arranged for violins in three and four parts with viola, cello, bass, piano ad lib. / Samuel Gardner. -- Boston, Mass.: Boston Music, c1946., 1 score (12 p.) + 7 parts; 31 cm. (Box 5, Folder 5)
      Corrections in pencil, erased.
      Contents: Frere Jacques and his jolly friends -- Nearer, my God, to thee (Lowell Mason) -- Long, long ago (Thomas H. Bayly) -- O little town of Bethlehem -- Silent night, holy night (Franz Gruber) -- America.
      Pl. no.: B.M.Co.10735
    - [Short pieces] Three short pieces; music for the violin with piano accompaniment, first position / Samuel Gardner. -- Boston, Mass.: Boston Music, c1945., 1 score (3 v.) + 1 part (3 v.); 31 cm (Box 5, Folder 6)
      For violin first position and piano.
      Covers signed and corrections in pencil.
      Contents: The melancholy flute -- Little waltz in D -- Babushka.
      Pl. no.: B.M.Co10614-6
    - [Sketches, violin, piano] Four sketches; easy first position pieces for vioin, with piano accompaniment / by Samuel Gardner. -- Boston, Mass.: Boston Music, c1954., 1 score (9 p.); 31 cm. (Box 5, Folder 7)
      On cover: "Graded to follow the Five miniatures."
      Signed and dated in pencil.
      Contents: Snowflakes -- Chimes at Christmas eve -- Wooden soldiers -- Memory of a swan.
      Pl. no.: B.M.Co.11069
    - [Harmonic thinking] School of violin study based on harmonic thinking as a means of acquiring musical development for tonal and technical mastery of the violin; intermediate to fairly advanced in the first position only / Samuel Gardner. -- New York: Carl Fischer, c1939., 1 score (2 v.); 31 cm. (Box 5, Folder 8)
      Violin exercises.
      On cover of Book II: Copy marked for intonation. Lib-research, S.G.
      Contents: Book I (Harmonic thinking) -- Book II (Harmonic and rhythmic thinking)
      Pl. no.: 28691-57; 28692-35
    - School of violin study. (Box 5, Folder 8)
      see [Harmonic thinking]
    - [Violin method] Violin method; a new approach for violin class or individual instruction; the first book, elementary to fairly advanced, first through fifth positions / Samuel Gardner. -- Boston, Mass.: Boston Music, c1947., 1 score([42 p.]): ills.; 31 cm. (Box 5, Folder 9)
      On cover: For lib. research
      Pl. no.: B.M.Co.10745
    - [Pedagogical sketches], 18 manuscript p. of music; various sizes. (Box 5, Folder 10)
      Sketches of violin exercises and educational works.
    - [Besame mucho] Besame mucho / arranged by Samuel Gardner., 1 manuscript score (7 p.) + 1 manuscript part (2 p.); 32 cm. (Box 5, Folder 11)
      Arr. for violin and piano.
  - Music by Others, I.C
    - [Old folks at home] Old folks at home = Swanee river / Stephen C. Foster; modernized concert arrangement by Samuel Gardner. -- New York: Carl Fischer, c1921., Foster, Stephen Collins, 1826-1864; 1 score (5 p.) + 1 part ([1 p.]); 30 cm. (Box 5, Folder 12)
      On cover: "Op. 3"
      2 copies of violin part, both with different markings.
      Pl. no.: 21861-5
    - [Etudes ou caprices, violin, no. 8, E major, arr.] Violin caprice, no. 8, in E major / by Rudolph Kreutzer; arranged for violin solo or violin group with piano or orchestra accompaniment by Samuel Gardner., Kreutzer, Rodolphe, 1766-1831; 1 manuscript score (11 p.); 32 cm. (Box 5, Folder 13)
      Arr. for violin solo or group of violins with orchestra.
      List of orchestra parts taped to inside cover of 1 copy.
    - [Etudes ou caprices, violin, no. 8, E major, arr.] Kreutzer violin caprice in E major / orchestra accompaniment Samuel Gardner., Kreutzer, Rodolphe, 1766-1831; 1 part (2 p.); 31 cm. (Box 5, Folder 14)
      Part for violin solo.
      Includes arranger's fingerings and dynamic revisions.
      17 copies.
    - [Etudes ou caprices, violin, no. 8, E major, arr.], Kreutzer, Rodolphe, 1766-1831; 30 manuscript parts; various sizes. (Box 5, Folder 15)
      Some parts are photocopies of manuscript
      Parts for: fl/ob/cl/bsn/hn/tpt/timp/harp/vlnI/vlnII/vla/vc/cb.
      Another set: 30 manuscript parts; 33 cm. Photocopies of holograph.
    - [Etudes ou caprices, violin, no. 8, E major, arr.] Violin caprice, no. 8, in E major / by Rodolphe Kreutzer; arranged for violin solo or violin group with piano or orchestra accompaniment by Samuel Gardner., Kreutzer, Rodolphe, 1766-1831; 1 manuscript score (4 p.); 32 cm. (Box 5, Folder 16)
      1 copy master sheets (printed in reverse)
    - [Night and day] Night and day / Cole Porter; arranged by Samuel Gardner., Porter, Cole, 1891-1964; 1 score (6 p.) + 1 part (2 p.); 31 cm. (Box 5, Folder 17)
      Score is photocopy of holograph.
      Another copy: Negative photostats of score (6 p.); 31 cm.
- Correspondence, Series II
  - To Gardner and others regarding Harmonic Thinking, II.A
    - Altvater, H. Hugh., October 12, 1939; typed letter signed (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Armstrong, Donald D., December 2, 1947; typed letter signed (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Betti, Adolpho, October 31, 1940; autograph letter signed xc (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Board of Education, Rochester, NY. Music Department. (Box 6, Folder 1)
      See Van Hoesen, Karl D.
    - Butler, Harold L., November 5, 1940; typed letter signed (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Columbia University. Department of Music. (Box 6, Folder 1)
      See Mason, Daniel Gregory
    - Columbia University. Teachers College. (Box 6, Folder 1)
      See
      Dykema, Peter W.
      Mursell, James L.
    - Damrosch, Walter, October 19, 1939; typed letter signed xc (Box 6, Folder 1)